{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This battle was formally ended when Charles O’Hara surrendered his sword to Benjamin Lincoln after trying to give it to Lincoln’s commander. This battle was preceded by a battle in which a fleet led by Thomas Graves was defeated by the Comte de Grasse, the Battle of the Chesapeake. For ten points, name this battle where Charles Cornwallis’s forces were defeated by George Washington, the last major battle of the American Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle or Siege of Yorktown",
        "German Battle A"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As a child, this ruler almost drowned in a pond after his mother, Anne of Austria, left him unsupervised. This ruler removed protections for Huguenots in France by revoking the Edict of Nantes. This ruler lost both the War of Devolution and the War of Spanish Succession and ruled with Cardinal Mazarin as his advisor. This ruler built the Palace of Versailles and once said “I am the state.” For ten points, name this longest-reigning French monarch known as the “Sun King.”",
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one of this man’s novels, Frederic Henry fights during the Battle of Caporetto. In another of his novRels, Robert Jordan rigs a bridge with dynamite during the Spanish Civil War. This member of the “Lost Generation” drew on his experiences as an ambulance driver during World War One for his novel A Farewell to Arms. When not at his home in Key West, this author frequently went on African safaris. For ten points, name this American author of For Whom the Bell Tolls and The Old Man and the Sea.",
      "answer": "Ernest Hemingway"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man died of a cerebral hemorrhage suffered in the House of Representatives while opposing a resolution to honor victorious Mexican-American War generals. An ardent abolitionist, this man argued Don behalf of slaves who had revolted in U.S. v. Schooner Amistad. As Secretary of State, this man inspired the Monroe Doctrine and negotiated a treaty with Louis Onis that included the purchase of Florida from Spain. For ten points, name this sixth president of the United States, whose father was the second president.",
      "answer": "John Quincy Adams"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city began as a small Akkadian settlement and grew under the Amorite dynasty in the 18th century BC. This city was captured by the Hittites and afterwards the Kassites, who renamed it Karanduniash. Sennacherib [sen-ACK-uh-rib] led a war against this city, whose sixth king established a code of law engraved on a seven foot tall, black stone stele. For ten points, name this city, once the site of the Ishtar Gate, ruled by Esarhaddon, Nabonidus [na-BOH-nih-duss], and Nebuchadnezzar II.",
      "answer": "Babylon T"
    },
    {
      "question": "Johann Peter Salomon gave this man’s 41st and final symphony the nickname Jupiter. This resident of Salzburg wrote a set of variations on a French folk song, later combined with words as “Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star.” According to legend, this man left his Requiem unfinished because he was poisoned by Antonio Salieri. The composer of A Little Night Music and the opera The Magic Flute, for ten points, F name this 18th-century Austrian composer and child prodigy.",
      "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
    },
    {
      "question": "One building in this city was designed by James Hoban and contains the Blue Room. This city’s streets were mapped out by Charles L’Enfant [lahn-FAHN], and it is home to a Maya Lin-designed wall with the names of casualties of the Vietnam War. In this city, the National Mall contains the Air and Space Museum and many other buildings owned by the Smithsonian Institution. For ten points, name A this city whose famous works of architecture include the U.S. Capitol and the White House.",
      "answer": [
        "Washington, D.C.",
        "D.C.",
        "District of Columbia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This company’s John Dustin Archbold was almost assassinated in 1915 at Cedar Cliffs by members of the IWW. The Florida East Coast Railway was developed by one of this company’s founders, Henry Flagler. Muckraker Ida Tarbell wrote a “History of” [this company].” This company was dissolved after it was found to be in violation of the Sherman Antitrust Act in 1911. For ten points, name this petroleum company that was created by John D. Rockefeller. R",
      "answer": "Standard Oil Company"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization was fined $500 for littering by the Esperance in Western Australia in 1979. This organization had intended that “litter” for a spot off the coast of South Africa, but it miscalculated how quickly debris from its more than 8 ton and 82 feet long piece of equipment would burn up upon re-entry. For ten points, name this American organization that put Skylab into orbit and anticipates a 2028 return to earth of the International Space Station.",
      "answer": [
        "National Aeronautics and Space Administration",
        "NASA D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The brothers Gyrth and Leofwine may have been killed early in this battle defending a shield wall composed of troops called fyrds. One side in this battle was massacred in the Malfosse after retreating. That side’s housecarls were able to hold Senlac Hill until an arrow to the eye killed their commander, Harold Godwinson. Depicted on the Bayeux Tapestry, for ten points, identify this 1066 battle that allowed William the Conqueror to take control of England.",
      "answer": "Battle of Hastings T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, James McFarlane was shot and killed at Bower Hill while attempting to surround and burn a key commander’s house. That man, John NFeville, was burned in effigy during this event, while Inspector Robert Johnson was tarred and feathered. After Governor Robert Mifflin refused to put down this insurrection, Lighthorse Harry Lee and the Watermelon Army were dispatched by George Washington to quash the rebel army. For ten points, name this rebellion in Western Pennsylvania sparked by an excise tax on the namesake type of alcohol.",
        "answer": [
          "Whiskey Rebellion",
          "Whiskey Insurrection"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A member of the Virginia militia who helped put down the rebellion was this man, named by Thomas Jefferson to lead anAexpedition across the continent.",
        "answer": "Meriwether Lewis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man began one war after raiding the Temple of Vesta and revealing his rival’s plans to have his sons control the empire. This founder of the Urban Cohorts constructed the Ara Pacis [PAH-chees] to celebrate the peaceful era of the Pax Romana. That era began after this man’s commander Marcus Agrippa was victorious over his rival, Marc Antony, at the battle of Actium. For ten points, name this adoptive son of Julius Caesar who became the first Roman emperor. R",
        "answer": [
          "Augustus Caesar",
          "Octavian",
          "Gaius Octavius"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This title, often given to the Pope and coming from the Latin for “bridge builder,” was taken by Augustus as the head of the Roman religion.",
        "answer": [
          "Pontiff",
          "Pontifex Maximus"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The beliefs of this Christian denomination were outlined in the Thirty Articles. Hugh Latimer and Nicholas Ridley were two martyrs of this denomination who were burned at the stake in the Marian D persecution after Catholic rule was restored. The Act of Supremacy empowered one leader of this denomination which draws heavily from the “Book of Common Prayer.” This denomination was created in response to Clement VII’s refusal to annul the marriage of Catherine of Aragon. For ten points, name this denomination formed by Henry VIII.",
        "answer": [
          "Anglican Church",
          "Anglicanism",
          "Church of England"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While the British monarch is the “Supreme Governor” of the Anglican Church, the Archbishop of this city is considered “first among equals” and is the de facto head of the church.",
        "answer": "Canterbury T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this period, translator Sidney Shapiro spent 10 years under house arrest for criticizing a political leader’s wife. “Scar literature” focuses on life during this period, during which The Legend of the Red Lantern and other examples of the eight model plays were widely performed. The play Hai Rui Dismissed from Office was criticized during this period after its overseer interpreted the work as Peng F Dehuai’s disapproval of the Great Leap Forward. For ten points, name this period in 1960s and 1970s China in which anti-capitalist literature was promoted by Chairman Mao.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution",
          "Wehnua Da Geming"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mao Zedong’s “Cult of Personality” was promoted by a book that was issued to all Chinese citizens, a “Little” book produced in this color.",
        "answer": "Red A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man likened Vladimir Putin to Hitler in his 2015 book Winter is Coming and entered his United Civil Front into the “Other Russia” coalition. In his earlier career, this man was defeated by a supercomputer known as “Deep Blue,” though he had earlier defeated Anatoly Karpov in 1985 to take the title of World Champion. For ten points, name this outspoken Armenian-Jewish chess grandmaster whose ELO rating was not surpassed until 2013 by Magnus Carlsen.",
        "answer": [
          "Garry Kasparov BORNUS: Deep Blue was created by this U.S. company that also created Watson and named it after this company’s founder. ANSWER: IBM",
          "International Business Machines Corporation 6 This island’s prominent usage of the Horns of Consecration motif was observed by Arthur Evans. “Snake goddess” sculptures found on this island by Evans are speculated to be household goddesses in this island’s neo-palatial culture. Inhabitants of this island often performed bull-dancing rituals, which were depicted on frescoes at Knossos. The script Linear B was used as a writing system on this island. D For ten points, name this largest Greek island, the center of the Minoan civilization. ANSWER: Crete"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The largest city on the island of Crete takes its name from this ancient mythological hero, known for slaying the Nemean Lion and capturing Cerberus among other labors.",
        "answer": [
          "Heracles",
          "Hercules T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The book Merchants of Labor chronicles the abuses of workers hired from this country. A minimum wage of 30 cents per hour was instituted as part of a program involving workers from this country which sought to increase contract labor when Americans were away fighting during World War Two. The end of that aforementioned Bracero program involving people from this country coincided with the rise of the F United Farm Workers. For ten points, name this country, home to such cities as Guadalajara and Tijuana.",
        "answer": [
          "Mexico",
          "United Mexican States,",
          "Estados Unidos Mexicanos,",
          "EUM"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Violence in the city of Tijuana in the 2000s caused many Mexicans to move to this U.S. city of some 1.5 million residents, 20 miles north of Tijuana.",
        "answer": "San Diego, California A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Judge John Sirica ordered James McCord to provide information about this event, which G. Gordon Liddy orchestrated as head of the Plumbers. During this event, Special Prosecutor Archibald Cox was fired in the Saturday Night Massacre, and the anonymous source “Deep Throat” aided journalists Woodward and Bernstein in uncovering this 1970s scandal. For ten points, name this scandal involving the wiretapping of Democrat Party headquarters at a certain Washington hotel that led to the resignation of Richard Nixon.",
        "answer": "Watergate scandal R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2020, a controversial book written by Bob Woodward that contains excerpts from recorded conversations with Donald Trump was published with this four-letter, one-word title.",
        "answer": "Rage"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Abolitionism in the United States",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Coerced labor system that it sought to end F",
          "answer": "Slavery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Escaped slave known as “Moses” who helped more than 70 people escape to the North",
          "answer": "Harriet Tubman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Abolitionist who published The Liberator and helped found the American Anti-Slavery Society",
          "answer": "William Lloyd Garrison A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Freed slave and abolitionist who wrote an 1845 best-selling Narrative of... his life",
          "answer": "Frederick Douglass"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who led the raid on a federal amory at Harper’s Ferry",
          "answer": "John Brown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Southern state, home of Henry Pinckney who authored the Congressional gag rule",
          "answer": "South Carolina R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Congregationalist clergyman who supplied rifles to abolitionists during Bleeding Kansas, his namesake Bibles",
          "answer": "Henry Ward Beecher"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of Abolitionists with financial connections who funded the raid on Harper’s Ferry",
          "answer": "Secret Six D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Fifth Republic",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who led the Free French in World War Two before founding the Fifth Republic F",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defensive alliance from which France withdrew in 1966",
          "answer": [
            "NATO",
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which a period of civil unrest occurred in May, involving student riots and a strike",
          "answer": "1968 A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longest serving and first Socialist president of the Republic",
          "answer": "Francois Mitterrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who won re-election over Jean-Marie Le Pen in a landslide in 2002",
          "answer": "Jacques Chirac"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lower house of the bicameral French Parliament",
          "answer": [
            "National Assembly",
            "Assemblee nationale R"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Greenpeace ship bombed by French Intelligence in 1985",
          "answer": "Rainbow Warrior"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central African Republic dictator who the French overthrew in Operation Barracuda",
          "answer": "Jean-Bedel Bokassa D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Warships",
      "prompt": "Which warship...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Fought the HMS Guerriere and was nicknamed “Old Ironsides” F",
          "answer": "USS Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sunk the HMS Hood before being hunted down by an Allied squadron",
          "answer": "Bismarck"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was sunk during the Attack on Pearl Harbor, the site of a memorial today",
          "answer": "USS Arizona A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a major mutiny in 1905 and the subject of a movie by Sergei Eisenstein",
          "answer": "Potemkin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the flagship of Horatio Nelson at the Battle of Trafalgar",
          "answer": "HMS Victory"
        },
        {
          "question": "Class of early 20th century battleships with a name meaning “fear nothing”",
          "answer": "Dreadnought R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Exploded in Havana Harbor in 1898, sparking the Spanish-American war",
          "answer": "USS Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the largest battleship ever built, sunk during Operation Ten-Go",
          "answer": "Yamato D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After John Humphrey Noyes kicked this man out of the Oneida community, he went to Hoboken, New Jersey to start an unsuccessfuFl newspaper called The Daily Theocrat. This author of the hymn “I am going to the Lordy,” (20 pts)",
        "pleaded for an ambassadorship to France, and this man’s most notable action resulted in the passage of the Pendleton Civil Service Act. “I am a (10 pts)",
        "stalwart of the stalwarts” was shouted by, for ten points, this man who fired two shots in the Baltimore and Potomac Railway Station to kill James Garfield."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles J. Guiteau"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While visiting Germany, this man once got so drunk that he started conducting a A celebratory band and blowing kisses to the crowd. This man’s vice president once referred to his reforms as “economic genocide.” Jesse Helms asked this man about the potential whereabouts of (20 pts)",
        "Larry MacDonald after an aerial incident under this man’s predecessor. This man, who released the KAL 007 black box, once stood in front of a (10 pts)",
        "tank to thwart a coup against his predecessor. For ten points, name this man who became the first president of Russia in 1991."
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin 3RIn a 2006 game against the Toronto Raptors, this man scored the second most points ever in a single game with 81. In 2018, this man became the first African-American to win the Academy Award for Best Animated Short Film for Dear + Basketball. Despite disagreements with teammate Shaquille O’Neal, this man won three NBA championships in a row from 2000 to 2002 and five in his career and became known as “The * Black Mamba.” For ten points, name this Los Angeles Laker who was killed in a helicopter crash in January, 2020. ANSWER: Kobe Bryant D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One policy established by this figure was influenced by the predictions of the Club of Rome. This leader opposed support for the “Fifth Modernization,” which was advocated by the Democracy Wall movement. The death of Hu (20 pts)",
        "Yaobang [‘who” yow-bahn] triggered a series of protests against this leader which ended with military intervention. That intervention included the determined stand of (10 pts)",
        "Tank Man. For ten points, name this Chinese leader who presided over the beginning of the one-child policy, the Tiananmen Square Massacre, and China’s liberalization in the 1980s."
      ],
      "answer": "Deng Xiaoping"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One city in this state has a twin city across the border in Moscow. One portion of this state including the town of Forks, formerly known primarily for logging, has become a notable tourist destination as it was the main setting of a series of novels by (20 pts)",
        "Stephenie Meyer. Larger cities in the center of this state include Ellensburg, Kennewick, and Moses Lake. The Whitman Massacre occurred in this state in 1847 near present-day (10 pts)",
        "Walla Walla. For ten points, name this state where Tacoma and the capital, Olympia, are both located."
      ],
      "answer": "Washington T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man and his brother served during the British invasion under Aulus Plautius where he commanded Legio II Augusta. That brother, Sabinus, was murdered in Rome while this man’s forces approached the city in the Year of the (20 pts)",
        "Four Emperors. This man was a patron of the historian Josephus, and he said right before his death in 79 AD that “an F Emperor ought to die standing upright.” The construction of the (10 pts)",
        "Colosseum began during this man’s reign and was finished during the reign of his successor, Titus. For ten points, name this founder of the Flavian dynasty."
      ],
      "answer": "Vespasian"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one poem by this author, “Stout and brave” hearts are likened to “muffled drums” after the speaker claims that “Life is real! Life is earnest! / And the grave is not the A goal.” This poet wrote about the title character’s love for Gabriel Lajeunesse as the British deported the (20 pts)",
        "Acadians during the Great Upheaval in a poem that begins “this is the forest primeval.” Ojibwe legends serve as the basis for a poem by this author that includes the title character’s marriage to (10 pts)",
        "Minniehaha. For ten points, name this American poet of “A Psalm of Life,” Evangeline, and The Song of Hiawatha."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry Wadsworth Longfellow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state, the Continental Army was trapped by the British behind Assinpink Creek buRt escaped by keeping their campfires lit while outflanking the British. Alexander Hamilton fired on (20 pts)",
        "Nassau Hall during a battle in this state at a university that had rejected him. One battle in this state was fought after George Washington’s army (10 pts)",
        "crossed the Delaware River on Christmas night. For ten points, name this state where the battles of Monmouth and Princeton were fought during the American Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "New Jersey"
    }
  ]
}